<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>

  <properties>
    <author email="jon@latchkey.com">Jon S. Stevens</author>
    <title>You make the decision - Changes</title>
  </properties>

<body>

<section name="Changes">

<p>
We are getting great feedback on this document. As promised, on the
homepage, this is a live document that will undergo changes over time to
correct mistakes and add improvements and clarifications. Below are a
list of changes to date (latest changes first in listing):
</p>

<p>
<ul>
<li>Rebuilt the helloworld.jsp example using Tomcat 3.3m2</li>
<li>Added Struts HelloWorld example from: <a
href="mailto:martin.cooper@tumbleweed.com">Martin Cooper</a></li>
<li>Integrated feedback from <a href="mailto:geirm@optonline.net">Geir
Magnusson Jr.</a></li>
<li>Integrated feedback from <a href="mailto:dion@multitask.com.au">dIon
Gillard</a></li>
<li>Typo fixes from <a href="mailto:tim@paneris.co.uk">Tim
Pizey</a></li>
<li>Cleanup of the way that the <a
href="./ymtd-implementation.html">Implementation</a> page 
is written in order to clarify the points.</li>
<li>Minor clarification in the <a
href="./ymtd-saying-hello.html">Saying Hello</a> example.</li>
<li>Added the <a href="./ymtd-hosting.html">Hosting</a> page to address
the idea that JSP makes a great hosting platform.</li>
<li>Added a paragraph on the <a 
href="./ymtd-conclusion.html">Conclusion</a> page.</li>
<li>Added a few paragraphs to the bottom of the <a 
href="./ymtd-taglibs.html">Taglibs</a> page.</li>
<li>Added a few paragraphs to the top of the <a 
href="./ymtd-sampleapp.html">Sample App</a> page.</li>
<li>Updated the example "right way" on the <a
href="./ymtd-saying-hello.html">Saying Hello</a> page as well as the
comments about it. Thanks to <a
href="mailto:niall.pemberton@btInternet.com">Niall Pemberton</a> for the
correction.</li>
<li>Added more clarification on the <a href="./ymtd.html">Home</a> page
about what we are comparing. The reason is that we got feedback from <a
href="mailto:niall.pemberton@btInternet.com">Niall Pemberton</a>
suggesting that because we didn't compare Internationalization that this
article was not of use for him.</li>
<li>Added a link to this page to the <a href="./ymtd.html">Home</a>
page.</li>
<li>Copy/paste error on the <a href="./ymtd-sampleapp.html">Sample
Application</a> page. (JSS)</li>
</ul>

</p>

<p>
<strong>[ Next -&gt; <a href="./ymtd.html">Home</a> ]</strong>
</p>

</section>

</body>
</document>
