<?xml version="1.0"?>

<document>

 <properties>
  <title>Velocity Changes</title>
  <author email="jon@latchkey.com">Jon S. Stevens</author>
 </properties>

<body>

<section name="Velocity Changes">

<p>
   This document tracks the changes in Velocity between releases.
</p>

<subsection name="1.0.1-dev">
<p>
Changes to version 1.0
</p>

<ul>
  <li> 
    Small fix to ASTGENode.java to catch NPE if LHS or RHS is null or not 
    int or Integer. (gmj)
  </li>
  <li>
    Added examples-clean-forumdemo target to build.xml for cleaning up 
    after building the forumdemo. (JSS)
  </li>
  <li> 
    Small fix to ASTAndNode.java to short circuit if LHS is false, and to 
    log an error of LHS or RHS is null. (gmj)
  </li>
</ul>

</subsection>
<subsection name="1.0b3">
<p>
   Released as version 1.0 on April 2, 2001
</p>

<ul>
   <li>
        Documentation: Fix the VTL Reference guide for the #if
        statement. Thanks to Joaquim Carvalho for the find. (JSS)
   </li>
   <li>
        Documentation: Fixed the html in the user guide that generates
        the TOC so that the numbers come out in proper order. (JSS)
   </li>
   <li>
       Added common base class for application-level exceptions in package
       org.apache.velocity.exception.  Thanks to Kyle Downey for the 
       suggestion.  (gmj)
    </li>
    <li>
       Added javadoc to o.a.v.context.AbstractContext clarifying which
       of the internalXXX methods are required.  Thanks to 
       Joshua Levy  for the suggestion. (gmj)
    </li>
    <li>
       Added license and javadoc to examples/context_example/DBContext.java
       to clarify why some internalXXX methods are stubbed out.  (gmj)
    </li>
    <li>
       Documentation : Clarification of VM properties and added note on
       VM declaration / usage order in user guide. (gmj)
    </li>
    <li>
       Fixed HttpServletRequestWrap.java - getInputStream() wasn't calling
       the method on the wrapped HttpServletRequest. Thanks to 
       Shahar Solomianik. (gmj)
    </li>
    <li>
       Removed build.compiler from the build.xml file. (JSS)
    </li>
    <li>
       Fixed problem found by jon where high concurrency would lead to 
       a dry parser pool, which would lead to vast unpleasantness masked
       as resource access errors.  All seems to be better now.  Simple
       fix, so little risk.  (gmj)
    </li>
    <li>
       Added <code>parser.pool.size</code> as a configuration parameter to
       help tune Velocity configurations for high concurrency loads. (gmj)
    </li>
    <li>
       Documentation : developers-guide - information/example on making a
       custom logger, and start of work on documenting resource loaders. (gmj)
     </li>
     <li>
       Removed some debugging gibberish from 
       InternalContextAdapterImpl.java (gmj)
     </li>
     <li>
       Committed John McNally's Texen patch to texen's Generator.java 
       to keep from accumulating introspection cache data in iterative 
       calls to parse() with template caching off. (gmj)
     </li>
     <li>
       Documentation : added some special-case Context information and a 
       secion on Vel and XML in the developers guide. (gmj)
      </li>
</ul>

</subsection>

<subsection name="1.0b2">

<p>
   Released as version 1.0 beta 2 on March 26, 2001
</p>

<ul> 
    <li>
        Make the distribution have CRLF for all of the text files (JSS).
    </li>
    <li>
        Fixed release packaging to create things in the right directory
        structure (JSS).
    </li>
    <li>
         Re-added 'include' support for Configuration. (JVZ)
    </li>
    <li>
         Fixed VMProxy bug when reference arg was null. (#1074) (gmj)
    </li>
    <li>
         Fixed nullpointer problem in cache refresh in ResourceManager 
	     (reported by Ilkka Priha) (gmj)
    </li>
    <li>
         VelocityServlet now respects the 'default.contentType' 
         property again.  That must have fallen out during the 'request 
         process' rework in VelServlet.  (reported by csterg@aias.gr) (gmj)
    </li>
    <li>
        Changed AnakiaTask and TexenTask to use the canonical 
        template file path rather than the literal string specified.  
        Motivated for ease of gump-tion.  Also added
        failonerror to the testcases.xml for the same reason. (gmj)
    </li>
    <li>
       Added Sam's suggestion for normalizing \n[\r] when comparing 
       results to expected results in the testbed via BaseTestCase  (gmj)
    </li>
    <li>
       Qualified import statments in Generator.java.  Added tests for 
       automatic boolean mapping in TexenTestCase.java. Added default 
       boolean mapping to texen for properties used with  the 
       contextProperties option.  Allow variants on boolean values in
       Configuration.java, and changes to relevant templates in testbed.
       Added default objects to context in TexenTask.java. (JVZ)
     </li>
     <li>
        Documentation changes to Configuration.java (DLR)
     </li>
     <li>
       Augmented the MethodInvocationException message in ASTMethod to 
       make the stacktraces more useful - noted from some traffic on 
       Turbine list.   (gmj)
     </li>
     <li>
         Added powered by logo. Look in
         xdocs/images/powered-by-logo.psd/.gif (JSS)
     </li>
     <li>
       Changed the internals of the Configuration class so that
       setProperty(K,V) will replace the value at K with V;
       addProperty(K,V) works the way setProperty(K,V) used
       to: if there is a value already stored at K then
       V is added to the vector. If nothing is being stored
       at K then the scalar V is simply added. setProperty(K,V)
       is basically a short form for clearProperty(K)/addProperty(K,V).
       Also added setConfiguration(C), so that an application using
       velocity could easily take a subset of the application
       configuration using C.subset(velocityProps) and set the
       whole velocity configuration at once. This is now how
       the velocity service works in Turbine. (JVZ)
     </li>

     <li>
       Added support to the Runtime/Velocity classes for
       addProperty(K,V). (JVZ)
     </li>
       
     <li>
       Added support to Runtime/Velocity classes for setConfiguration.
       (JVZ)
     </li>
     
     <li>
        Confirmed that the build.bat works on Win98 as well as made the
        classpath that the build.bat generates equal to the one that
        build.sh generates. (JSS)
     </li>
</ul>
</subsection>

<subsection name="1.0b1">
<ul>
    <li>
        Initial release.
    </li>
</ul>
</subsection>

</section>

</body>
</document>
