<?xml version="1.0"?>

<document>

 <header>
  <title>Coding Standards</title>
  <subtitle>Coding Standards</subtitle>
  <authors>
   <person name="Velocity Documentation Team" email="jvanzyl@locus.apache.org"/>
  </authors>
 </header>

<body>

<s1 title="Coding Standards">

<p>
    Code submissions to the Velocity project must follow the conventions 
    listed in this document. Velocity developers 
    are asked to follow coding conventions already present in the code. 
    For example, if the existing code has the bracket on
    the same line as the if statement, then all subsequent code
    should also follow that convention. Anything not 
    explicitly mentioned in this document should follow the official
    <link href="http://java.sun.com/docs/codeconv/html/CodeConvTOC.doc.html">Sun
    Java Coding Conventions</link>. 
</p>

<p>
    <strong>If you are caught commiting code that does not follow 
    the existing conventions, you will be responsible for fixing 
    it.</strong>
</p>

<p>
1. Brackets should begin and end on new lines. Examples:
</p>

<p>
<source><![CDATA[

if ( foo )
{
    // code here
}    

try
{
    // code here
}
catch (Exception bar)
{
    // code here
}
finally
{
    // code here
}    

while ( true )
{
    // code here
}    
]]></source>
</p>

<p>
2. Spaces between parentheses are optional. The preference is to exclude 
extra spaces. For example, both of these conventions are acceptable:
</p>

<p>
<source><![CDATA[

if (foo)

or

if ( foo )
]]></source>
</p>

<p>
3. Four spaces. <strong>NO</strong> tabs. Period. The Velocity 
mailing list receives cvs commit messages that are almost impossible 
to read if tabs are used.
</p>

<p>
In Emacs-speak, this translates to the following command:

(setq-default tab-width 4 indent-tabs-mode nil)
</p>

<p>
4. Use Unix linefeeds for all .java source code files. Only platform-specific
files (e.g. .bat files for Windows) should contain non-Unix linefeeds.
</p>

<p>
5. Javadoc <strong>MUST</strong> exist on all your methods. Contributing
a missing javadoc for any method, class, variable, etc., will be greatly
appreciated as this will help to improve the Velocity project.
</p>

<p>
6. The Jakarta Apache/Velocity License <strong>MUST</strong> be placed 
at the top of every file.
</p>

</s1>

</body>
</document>
