<?xml version="1.0"?>

<document>

 <header>
  <title>Coding Standards</title>
  <subtitle>Coding Standards</subtitle>
  <authors>
   <person name="Velocity Documentation Team" email="jvanzyl@locus.apache.org"/>
  </authors>
 </header>

<body>

<s1 title="Coding Standards">

<p>
    This document describes a list of coding conventions that are required
    for code submissions to the project. By default, the coding conventions
    for most Open Source Projects should follow the existing coding conventions
    in the code that you are working on. For example, if the bracket is on
    the same line as the if statement, then you should write all your code
    to have that convention.<strong></strong>
</p>

<p>
    <strong>If you commit code that does not follow these conventions and you
    are caught, you are responsible for also fixing your own code.</strong>
</p>

<p>
    Below is a list of coding conventions that are specific to Turbine,
    everything else not specificially mentioned here should follow the official
    <link href="http://java.sun.com/docs/codeconv/html/CodeConvTOC.doc.html">Sun
    Java Coding Conventions</link>.
</p>

<p>
1. Brackets should begin and end on a new line. Examples:
</p>

<p>
<source><![CDATA[

if ( foo )
{
    // code here
}    

try
{
    // code here
}
catch (Exception bar)
{
    // code here
}
finally
{
    // code here
}    

while ( true )
{
    // code here
}    
]]></source>
</p>

<p>
2. It is <strong>OK</strong> to have spaces between the parens or not. The preference
is to not include the extra spaces. For example, both of these are ok:
</p>

<p>
<source><![CDATA[

if (foo)

or

if ( foo )
]]></source>
</p>

<p>
3. 4 spaces. <strong>NO</strong> tabs. Period. We understand that a lot of you like
to use tabs, but the fact of the matter is that in a distributed development
enviroment, when the cvs commit messages get sent to a mailing list, they
are almost impossible to read if you use tabs.
</p>

<p>
In Emacs-speak, this translates to the following command:

(setq-default tab-width 4 indent-tabs-mode nil)
</p>

<p>
4. Unix linefeeds for all .java source code files. Other platform specific
files should have the platform specific linefeeds.
</p>

<p>
5. Javadoc <strong>MUST</strong> exist on all your methods. Also, if you are working
on existing code and there currently isn't a javadoc for that method/class/variable
or whatever, then you should contribute and add it. This will improve the
project as a whole.
</p>

<p>
6. The Jakarta Apache/Velocity License <strong>MUST</strong> be placed at the top
of each and every file.
</p>

</s1>

</body>
</document>
