<?xml version="1.0"?>

<document>

 <properties>
  <title>Velocity Getting Started</title>
  <author email="jvanzyl@zenplex.com">Velocity Documentation Team</author>
 </properties>

<body>


<section name="Getting Started">

<p>
  It's easy to get started with Velocity.   The best places to begin are:

  <ul>
   <li>
      the <a href="user-guide.html">User's Guide</a>, which provides a good
      overview of what Velocity templates are all about.
   </li>
   <li>
     the <a href="developer-guide.html">Developer's Guide</a>, which provides
     a good reference and discussion of how to incorporate Velocity into your Java
     programs and servlets.
   </li>
   <li>
     the <a href="vtl-reference-guide.html">VTL Reference Guide</a>, which is a reference
     guide to VTL, the Velocity Template Language.
   </li>
   <li>
     if you want to build a web application, be sure to read the <a href="webapps.html">Web Application Guide</a>
     and then download the <a href="">Velocity Tools</a> sub-project to use VelocityViewServlet.
    </li>
   </ul>

    
   The best place to start is with the examples provided in the distribution,
   and with the source code itself, which is included.
</p>


</section>
<section name="Downloading Velocity">
    <p>
        You can download the latest release version of 
        <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/site/downloads/downloads_velocity-engine.cgi">Velocity</a> 
        or <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/site/downloads/downloads_velocity-tools.cgi">Velocity Tools</a> 
        from the main Jakarta download site.  For Velocity itself, source is included with the binary download.
    </p>

    <p>
        If you want to download the latest source, you can do so via the Subversion (svn) 
        source control system, or download a complete 
        <a href="http://cvs.apache.org/snapshots/velocity/">nightly snapshot.</a>
    </p>

    <p>
        Instructions for building Velocity from source can be found in the
        <a href="build.html">Build</a> document.
    </p>

</section>

<section name="API Documentation">

<p>
Our API documentation is available <a href="api/index.html">online</a>, 
as part of the distribution package, and of course, you can generate it
yourself from the included source code.
</p>
<p>
    If you would like to create a full set
    of detailed API documentation for Velocity, go to the
    <code>build</code> directory and run:
</p>

<source><![CDATA[
ant javadocs
]]></source>

<p>
The docs will be found in the <code>/docs/apidocs/</code> directory.
</p>

<p>
<b>Note:</b> Velocity uses the <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/ant/">Jakarta Ant</a> 
build tool for all code and documentation generation, so you will need to have it 
installed.  We strongly endorse this wonderful tool for any Java developer.
   </p>

</section>

</body>
</document>
