<?xml version="1.0"?>

<document>

 <properties>
  <title>Velocity</title>
  <author email="jvanzyl@locus.apache.org">Velocity Documentation Team</author>
 </properties>

 <body>

 <section name="What is Velocity?">

 <p>
    Velocity is a Java-based template engine. It permits web page designers
    to use simple yet powerful template language to reference objects
    defined in Java code. Web designers can work in parallel with Java
    programmers to develop web sites according to the Model-View-Controller
    (MVC) model, meaning that web page designers can focus solely on creating
    a site that looks good, and programmers can focus solely on writing
    top-notch code. Velocity separates Java code from the web pages,
    making the web site more maintainable over the long run and providing
    a viable alternative to
    <a href="http://java.sun.com/products/jsp/">Java Server Pages</a>
    (JSPs) or <a href="http://www.php.net/">PHP</a>.
 </p>

 <p>
    Velocity's capabilities reach well beyond the realm of web sites; for
    example, it can generate SQL and PostScript and XML (see <a
    href="./anakia.html">Anakia</a> for more information on XML transformations)
    from templates.  It can be used either as a standalone utility for
    generating source code and reports, or as an integrated component of other
    systems. When complete, Velocity will provide template services for the
    <a href="http://java.apache.org/turbine/">Turbine</a> web application
    framework. Velocity+Turbine will provide a template service that will allow
    web applications to be developed according to a true MVC model.
 </p>

 </section>



<section name="Where do I get releases?">

<p>
    There is no official release yet, but there will be one
    shortly. The full source can be retrieved via <a
    href="http://jakarta.apache.org/getinvolved/cvsindex.html">CVS</a>.
</p>

</section>

<section name="Where do I get nightly builds?">

<p>
    Nightly builds of Velocity can be found
    <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/builds/jakarta-velocity/nightly/">here</a>.
</p>

</section>

<section name="How do I contribute, give feedback, fix bugs and so on?">

<p>
    The Velocity project really needs and appreciates any contributions,
    including documentation help, source code and feedback. Suggested
    changes should come in the form of source code and/or very detailed
    and constructive feedback.
</p>

<ul>
    <li>
        There is a list of <a href="contributors.html">Active Developers</a>.
        Submit some code and get your name added!</li>
    <li>
        Discussion occurs on the <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/getinvolved/mail.html">Velocity mailing
        list</a>.</li>
    <li>
        Access to the CVS <strong>jakarta-velocity</strong> repository is available both
        <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/cvsweb/index.cgi/jakarta-velocity/">online</a>
        and with a <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/getinvolved/cvsindex.html">cvs client</a>.</li>
</ul>

</section>

 </body>
 </document>
