<?xml version="1.0"?>

<document>

 <header>
  <title>Velocity</title>
  <subtitle>Velocity</subtitle>
  <authors>
   <person name="Velocity Documentation Team" email="jvanzyl@locus.apache.org"/>
  </authors>
 </header>

 <body>

 <s1 title="What is Velocity?">

 <p>
    Velocity is a Java-based template engine. It can be used as a
    standalone utility for generating source code, HTML, reports,
    or it can be combined with other systems to provide template
    services. Velocity will be tightly integrated with the 
    <link href="http://java.apache.org/turbine/">Turbine</link>
    web application framework to provide a template service that 
    will enable a true MVC model by which web applications may be 
    developed.
 </p>    
    
 <p>    
    Velocity uses a grammar-based parser generated by 
    <link href="http://www.metamata.com/javacc/">JavaCC</link>
    (Java Compiler Compiler) using the JJTree extension to create an
    Abstract Syntax Tree (AST). The AST may subsequently be traversed
    (repeatedly if desired) by a tree walker, which
    is implemented using the visitor design pattern. This allows
    the parsing logic to be separated from the actions performed
    on the resultant AST. Two visitors come with Velocity: the first 
    is a simple implementation that produces a visual tree of the 
    syntax and nothing more, mostly used for
    debugging; the second visitor actually generates
    output from user-defined values and introspection.
 </p>

 </s1>



<s1 title="Where do I get releases?">

<p>
    There is no official release yet, but there will be one
    shortly. The full source can be retrieved via <link
    href="http://jakarta.apache.org/getinvolved/cvsindex.html">CVS</link>.
</p>

</s1>

<s1 title="Where do I get nightly builds?">

<p>
    You can find nightly builds
    <link href="http://jakarta.apache.org/builds/jakarta-velocity/nightly/">here</link>.
</p>    

</s1>

<s1 title="How do I contribute, give feedback, fix bugs and so on?">

<p>
    We really need and appreciate any contributions you can give, including
    documentation help, source code and feedback. Discussion about changes
    should come in the form of source code and/or very detailed and well thought
    out constructive feedback.
</p>

<ul>
    <li>
        We have a complete list of <link href="contributors.html">Active Developers</link>.
        Submit some code and get your name added!</li>
    <li>
        We have a <link href="http://jakarta.apache.org/getinvolved/mail.html">Velocity mailing
        list</link> for discussion.</li>
    <li>
        Access to the CVS "<strong>jakarta-velocity</strong>" repository is available both 
        <link href="http://jakarta.apache.org/cvsweb/index.cgi/jakarta-velocity/">online</link>
        as well as with a <link href="http://jakarta.apache.org/getinvolved/cvsindex.html">cvs client</link>.</li>
</ul>

</s1>

 </body>
 </document>
