<?xml version="1.0"?>

<document>

 <properties>
  <title>Velocity</title>
  <author email="jvanzyl@zenplex.com">Velocity Documentation Team</author>
 </properties>

 <body>

<section name="Velocity v1.2 Released">

 <p>
   <table>
   <tr>
   <td>
   <img src="images/powered-by-logo.gif" alt="powered-by-logo.gif" width="77" height="32"/>
   </td>
   <td>
   Version 1.2 of the
   Velocity Template Engine is now available.
   Thanks to all in the Velocity community who made
   this release a success.
   </td>
   </tr>
   </table>
 </p>

 <p>
   Combining contributions from throughout the
   Velocity community, this version offers many new enhancements,
   features and fixes over version 1.1.
 </p>
 <p>
   Major enhancements include :
 </p>

 <ul>
   <li>
      Application programmers now can instantiate separate, independent
      instances of the Velocity Template Engine or continue to use the
      traditional singleton model.
   </li>
   <li>
      Major improvements to Anakia and Texen.
   </li>
   <li>
      The Velocimacro system can be configured to reload changed
      VM libraries automatically when the macro definitions change.
   </li>
 </ul>
 <p>
   Minor enhancements are too numerous to mention. Please see the
   <a href="changes.html">change log
   </a> for details.
</p>

<p>
 <b>Note:</b> This release now requires
 <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/ant/">Ant 1.4</a>
 to build the source and/or use the testbed.
 As before, <i>using Velocity</i> does not require Ant.
</p>

</section>

<section name="Velocity News">


<p>
 <strong>DVSL XML Transformation Tool Added as Subproject</strong>
 <blockquote>
 The DVSL XML transformation tool has been added as a new subproject.
 Check it out <a href="/velocity/dvsl/index.html">here</a>.(<i>2001-12-18</i>)
 </blockquote>
</p>
<p>
  <strong>Velocity mentioned in ZDNet Article (last May)</strong>
<blockquote>
  It seems we could be a "can't-live-without-it piece of the
infrastructure" of tomorrow. Check
<a href="http://www.zdnet.com/zdnn/stories/news/0,4586,2717910,00.html">
it</a> out. <i>(2001-12-09)</i>
</blockquote>
</p>

<p>
  <strong>Luxor, Velocity-based XUL Toolkit Released</strong>
  <blockquote>
    Luxor is an open-source XML User Interface Language (XUL) toolkit for
    Java. Read more <a href="http://luxor-xul.sourceforge.net">here</a>.
    <i>(2001-12-08)</i>
  </blockquote>
</p>
<p>
<strong>Generate Code with Velocity in Borland's JBuilder </strong>
<blockquote>
  <a href="http://community.borland.com/article/0,1410,28086,00.html">Read</a>
  about how to use Velocity and Borland's OpenTools API to extend Borland's
  JBuilder for template-based Java source code generation. <i>(2001-12-08)</i>
</blockquote>
</p>

<p>
<strong>Hey, Maybe We're On The Right Track After All...</strong>
<blockquote>
Give <a href="http://www.caucho.com/products/resin/ref/velocity.xtp">this</a>
a read.  The latest version of <a href="http://www.caucho.com/">Resin</a>, a
popular servlet engine, has added what they call a "Velocity-like syntax" to their JSP
implementation.  As they say on their site :
<blockquote>
<i>"The Resin-2.0.3 release allows an alternate JSP expression syntax similar to the Apache Velocity project that many find more maintainable than the JSP pointy brackets. Resin's syntax extension is compatible with the usual JSP features like tag libraries."
</i>
</blockquote>

We do think that this is a step in the right direction for JSPs, making the page content easier to
write and maintain.
<br/>
<br/>
However, we want to emphasize to users that this isn't the same thing as using
Velocity - this is a small subset of the Velocity syntax which
was reimplemented in Resin.
<br/>
<br/>
 Velocity is much more than an alternative syntax to the scriptlets and
tags found in JSPs - it's a full-featured templating engine, fully portable to any
J2EE servlet container, that offers many advanges over JSPs in the J2EE
web application environment.  It also an excellent templating tool
for other kinds of applications written in Java.
<br/>
<br/>
So if you are interested in portable alternatives to JSP, we strongly
encourage you look deeper into what Velocity has to offer.
<br/>
<br/>
And if you must use JSPs and want to incorporate Velocity into your
current or new JSP-based web applications, take a look at our
<a href="veltag.html">Veltag</a> JSP taglib which allows the full
power of Velocity in your JSPs.
</blockquote>
</p>

<p>
<i>Archived articles are <a href="/newshistory.html">here</a></i>.
</p>

 </section>

 <section name="What is Velocity?">

 <p>
    Velocity is a Java-based template engine. It permits anyone to use
    the simple yet powerful template language to reference objects
    defined in Java code.
 </p>

 <p>
    When Velocity is used for web development, Web designers can work in
    parallel with Java programmers to develop web sites according to the
    Model-View-Controller (MVC) model, meaning that web page designers
    can focus solely on creating a site that looks good, and programmers
    can focus solely on writing top-notch code. Velocity separates Java
    code from the web pages, making the web site more maintainable over
    the long run and providing a viable alternative to <a
    href="http://java.sun.com/products/jsp/">Java Server Pages</a>
    (JSPs) or <a href="http://www.php.net/">PHP</a>.
 </p>

 <p>
    Velocity's capabilities reach well beyond the realm of web sites; for
    example, it can generate SQL and PostScript and XML (see <a
    href="./anakia.html">Anakia</a> for more information on XML transformations)
    from templates.  It can be used either as a standalone utility for
    generating source code and reports, or as an integrated component of other
    systems.  Velocity also provides template services for the
    <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/turbine/">Turbine</a> web application
    framework. Velocity+Turbine  provides a template service that allows
    web applications to be developed according to a true MVC model.
 </p>

 </section>



<section name="Where do I get releases?">

<p>
   The current release version is version 1.2
</p>

<p>
The release distribution is available in both <code>tar.gz</code> and <code>zip</code>
formats, and are found <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/builds/jakarta-velocity/release/v1.2/">here</a>.
</p>

</section>

<section name="Where do I get nightly snapshots?">

<p>
    Nightly snapshots of the Velocity CVS can be found
    <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/builds/jakarta-velocity/nightly/">here</a>.
</p>

<p>
These are meant to provide easy access to the actual project CVS tree.
As this is our live development workspace, there are no guarantees as to
what you will find there,although we do our best to maintain a buildable
source tree. If you are looking for the stable supported release, please
use the current release of Velocity.
</p>

<p>
If you are willing to risk getting dirty, we invite you to try the
nightly snapshot to see the current state of affairs (and help out!) <a
href="http://jakarta.apache.org/site/cvsindex.html">Public CVS
access</a> is also available.
</p>

</section>

<section name="How do I contribute, give feedback, fix bugs and so on?">

<p>
    The Velocity project really needs and appreciates any contributions,
    including documentation help, source code and feedback. Suggested
    changes should come in the form of source code and/or very detailed
    and constructive feedback.
</p>

<ul>
    <li>
        There is a list of <a href="contributors.html">Active Developers</a>.
        Submit some code and get your name added!</li>
    <li>
        Discussion occurs on the <a
        href="http://jakarta.apache.org/getinvolved/mail.html">Velocity
        mailing list</a>.</li>
    <li>
        Access to the CVS <strong>jakarta-velocity</strong> repository is available both
        <a href="http://cvs.apache.org/viewcvs/jakarta-velocity/">online</a>
        and with a <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/getinvolved/cvsindex.html">cvs client</a>.</li>
</ul>

</section>

 </body>
 </document>





