<?xml version="1.0"?>

<document>

 <properties>
  <title>Velocity</title>
  <author email="jvanzyl@locus.apache.org">Velocity Documentation Team</author>
 </properties>

 <body>

<section name="Velocity v1.1 Released">

 <p>
   <table>
   <tr>
   <td>
   <img src="images/powered-by-logo.gif" alt="powered-by-logo.gif" width="77" height="32"/>
   </td>
   <td>
   Version 1.1 of the 
   Velocity Template Engine is now released.
   Congratulations and thanks to all participants in the
   Velocity community.
   </td>
   </tr>
   </table>      
 </p>

 <p>
   Major enhancements include :
 </p>

 <ul>
   <li> 
      The new event-handling facility, allowing finer control and interaction with
      the rendering process.
   </li>
   <li> 
      Internationalization support through full support of template character encoding.
   </li>
   <li> 
      Optimizations for improved performance.
   </li>
 </ul>
 <p> 
   Minor enhancements are too numerous to mention. Please see the
   <a href="changes.html">change log
   </a> for details.
</p>

</section>

<section name="Velocity in the News">
<p>
  The Sun <i>Dot-Com Builder</i> developer information site just did a "Best Practices" product profile on Velocity.  Check it out 
  <a href=" http://dcb.sun.com/practices/profiles/velocity.jsp">here.</a>  Thanks Sun!
</p>

 </section>
 <section name="What is Velocity?">

 <p>
    Velocity is a Java-based template engine. It permits anyone to use
    the simple yet powerful template language to reference objects
    defined in Java code.
 </p>
 
 <p>
    When Velocity is used for web development, Web designers can work in
    parallel with Java programmers to develop web sites according to the
    Model-View-Controller (MVC) model, meaning that web page designers
    can focus solely on creating a site that looks good, and programmers
    can focus solely on writing top-notch code. Velocity separates Java
    code from the web pages, making the web site more maintainable over
    the long run and providing a viable alternative to <a
    href="http://java.sun.com/products/jsp/">Java Server Pages</a>
    (JSPs) or <a href="http://www.php.net/">PHP</a>.
 </p>

 <p>
    Velocity's capabilities reach well beyond the realm of web sites; for
    example, it can generate SQL and PostScript and XML (see <a
    href="./anakia.html">Anakia</a> for more information on XML transformations)
    from templates.  It can be used either as a standalone utility for
    generating source code and reports, or as an integrated component of other
    systems.  Velocity also provides template services for the
    <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/turbine/">Turbine</a> web application
    framework. Velocity+Turbine  provides a template service that will allow
    web applications to be developed according to a true MVC model.
 </p>

 </section>



<section name="Where do I get releases?">

<p> 
   The current release version is version 1.1
</p>

<p>
The release distribution is available in both <code>tar.gz</code> and <code>zip</code>
formats, and are found <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/builds/jakarta-velocity/release/v1.1/">here</a>.
</p>


</section>

<section name="Where do I get nightly snapshots?">

<p>
    Nightly snapshots of the Velocity CVS can be found
    <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/builds/jakarta-velocity/nightly/">here</a>.
</p>

<p>
These are meant to provide easy access to the actual project CVS tree.
As this is our live development workspace, there are no guarantees as to
what you will find there,although we do our best to maintain a buildable
source tree. If you are looking for the stable supported release, please
use the current release of Velocity.
</p>

<p>
If you are willing to risk getting dirty, we invite you to try the
nightly snapshot to see the current state of affairs (and help out!) <a
href="http://jakarta.apache.org/site/cvsindex.html">Public CVS
access</a> is also available.
</p>

</section>

<section name="How do I contribute, give feedback, fix bugs and so on?">

<p>
    The Velocity project really needs and appreciates any contributions,
    including documentation help, source code and feedback. Suggested
    changes should come in the form of source code and/or very detailed
    and constructive feedback.
</p>

<ul>
    <li>
        There is a list of <a href="contributors.html">Active Developers</a>.
        Submit some code and get your name added!</li>
    <li>
        Discussion occurs on the <a
        href="http://jakarta.apache.org/getinvolved/mail.html">Velocity
        mailing list</a>.</li>
    <li>
        Access to the CVS <strong>jakarta-velocity</strong> repository is available both
        <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/cvsweb/index.cgi/jakarta-velocity/">online</a>
        and with a <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/getinvolved/cvsindex.html">cvs client</a>.</li>
</ul>

</section>

 </body>
 </document>





