<?xml version="1.0"?>

<!--
   Copyright 2000-2004 The Apache Software Foundation

   Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
   you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
   You may obtain a copy of the License at

       http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

   Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
   distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
   WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
   See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
   limitations under the License.
-->


<document>

 <properties>
  <title>Velocity</title>
  <author email="geirm@apache.org">Velocity Documentation Team</author>
 </properties>

 <body>


<section name="Older Velocity News">

<p>
<strong>Hey, Maybe We're On The Right Track After All...</strong>
<blockquote>
Give <a href="http://www.caucho.com/products/resin/ref/velocity.xtp">this</a>
a read.  The latest version of <a href="http://www.caucho.com/">Resin</a>, a
popular servlet engine, has added what they call a "Velocity-like syntax" to their JSP
implementation.  As they say on their site :
<blockquote>
<i>"The Resin-2.0.3 release allows an alternate JSP expression syntax similar to the Apache Velocity project that many find more maintainable than the JSP pointy brackets. Resin's syntax extension is compatible with the usual JSP features like tag libraries."
</i>
</blockquote>

We do think that this is a step in the right direction for JSPs, making the page content easier to
write and maintain.
<br/>
<br/>
However, we want to emphasize to users that this isn't the same thing as using
Velocity - this is a small subset of the Velocity syntax which
was reimplemented in Resin.
<br/>
<br/>
 Velocity is much more than an alternative syntax to the scriptlets and
tags found in JSPs - it's a full-featured templating engine, fully portable to any
J2EE servlet container, that offers many advanges over JSPs in the J2EE
web application environment.  It also an excellent templating tool
for other kinds of applications written in Java.
<br/>
<br/>
So if you are interested in portable alternatives to JSP, we strongly
encourage you look deeper into what Velocity has to offer.
<br/>
<br/>
And if you must use JSPs and want to incorporate Velocity into your
current or new JSP-based web applications, take a look at our
<a href="veltag.html">Veltag</a> JSP taglib which allows the full
power of Velocity in your JSPs.
</blockquote>
</p>


<p>
<strong>Velocidoc Released</strong>
<blockquote>
<a href="http://velocidoc.sourceforge.net/intro.html">
Velocidoc</a>, a Velocimacro documentation tool modeled after
Javadoc, is now available.  Use Javadoc-style comments in your
Velocimacro libraries, and use Velocidoc to generate HTML
documentation.
</blockquote>
</p>

<p>
<strong>New Apache Site Generated with Anakia</strong>
<blockquote>
The new web site of the
<a href="http://www.apache.org">Apache Software Foundation</a>
is now generated using
<a href="anakia.html">Anakia</a>,
the Velocity-based XML transformation tool.
Take a look.
</blockquote>
</p>

<p>
<strong>Need To Mix JSP and Velocity?</strong>
<blockquote>
Take a look at a new contribution, a
<a href="veltag.html">Velocity taglib</a> that lets you
use Velocity right in your JSPs.
</blockquote>
</p>

<p>
<strong>4 published articles covering Velocity</strong>
</p>

<blockquote>
<a href="http://www.webtechniques.com/archives/2001/09/serv/">Getting Up
to Speed with Velocity</a> is a really well written article by Jim
Jagielski about the merits of using a tool like Velocity.
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
Many people believe that Velocity can only be used in the context of web
applications. This excellent <a
href="http://www.javaworld.com/javaworld/jw-07-2001/jw-0727-templates.html">JavaWorld
article</a> by Leon Messerschmidt shows that the design of Velocity is
such that it can be used in a myriad of applications.
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
The Java Developer Journal recently <a
href="http://www.sys-con.com/java/articlea.cfm?id=1080">published</a> an
edited version of the <a href="./ymtd/ymtd.html">YMTD article</a> by Jon
Stevens as the cover story for their July edition.
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  The Sun <i>Dot-Com Builder</i> developer information site has a "Best Practices" product profile on Velocity.  Check it out
  <a href=" http://dcb.sun.com/practices/profiles/velocity.jsp">here</a>.  Thanks Sun!
</blockquote>

<p>
<strong> 4 Products/Projects Now Depend on Velocity </strong>
</p>
<blockquote>
Gentleware, Xadra and Vamp have built products which depend on Velocity.
J/Top, a server monitoring project, also uses Velocity for email output
formatting.
We have listed them on our ever expanding <a
href="./powered.html">Powered By Velocity</a> page.
</blockquote>

<p>
<strong> 5 Web Frameworks Now Support Velocity </strong>
</p>
<blockquote>
Turbine, JPublish, Melati, Maverick and WebWork
all support Velocity.
We have listed them on our ever expanding <a
href="./powered.html">Powered By Velocity</a> page.
</blockquote>

 </section>


 </body>
 </document>





