<?xml version="1.0"?>

<!--
   Copyright 2000-2004 The Apache Software Foundation

   Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
   you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
   You may obtain a copy of the License at

       http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

   Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
   distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
   WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
   See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
   limitations under the License.
-->


<document>
 <properties>
  <title>Velocity powered Websites</title>
  <author email="jon@latchkey.com">Jon S. Stevens</author>
 </properties>

 <body>

 <section name="Powered-By Velocity Logo">

 <p>
   This is not a requirement, but we would love it if you would adopt
   our Powered-By Velocity logo for your own website in order to show
   your support for our hard work.
 </p>

 <p>
 <img src="images/powered-by-logo.gif" alt="Powered By Velocity" width="77" height="32" />
 </p>

 </section>

 <section name="Velocity-powered Products and Projects">
 <p>
   Velocity is a utility tool which can be used in conjunction with
   general applications which may or may not be web based.
 </p>

 <table>
   <tr>
    <td><b>Name</b></td>
    <td><b>Description</b></td>
   </tr>

   <tr>
    <td>
     <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/velocity/anakia.html">Anakia</a>
    </td>
    <td>
       Essentially an XML transformation tool, Anakia uses JDOM and Velocity
       to transform XML documents into the format of your choice. It provides
       an alternative to using Ant's &lt;style&gt; task and XSL to process XML files.
    </td>
   </tr>

   <tr>
    <td>
     <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/velocity/texen.html">Texen</a>
    </td>
    <td>
      Texen is a general purpose text generating utility. It is capable of
      producing almost any sort of text output. Driven by Ant, Texen uses
      a control template, an optional set of worker templates, and control
      context to govern the generated output.
    </td>
   </tr>

   <tr>
    <td>
     <a href="http://www.gentleware.com/products/index.php3">GentleWare</a> Poseidon for UML
    </td>
    <td>
     GentleWare's Poseidon product uses Velocity as a template tool in
     order to generate Java code from UML diagrams that you design using
     their tool.
    </td>
   </tr>

   <tr>
    <td>
     <a href="http://www.xadra.com/products/vas/index.html">Xadra</a> VelocityAdaptorServer
    </td>
    <td>
     The VelocityAdaptorServer is a very simple yet extremely flexible
     system for the creation of HTML-based Java Management
     Extensions[tm] (JMX) compatible management consoles.
    </td>
   </tr>

   <tr>
    <td>
     <a href="http://www.vamphq.com/">Venus Application Publisher (Vamp)</a>
    </td>
    <td>
        Vamp is a user-friendly tool that helps you package, sign and publish Web
        Start/Java Network Launching Protocol (JNLP) software. Vamp uses Velocity
        heavily to create parts of the gooey (GUI) in XUL or HTML or to create
        documents such as JNLP startup files, web app config files or
        HTML info pages.
    </td>
   </tr>

   <tr>
    <td>
     <a href="http://jtop.sourceforge.net/">J/Top</a>
    </td>
    <td>
    J/Top is an open source application for monitoring multiple servers running
    'top'.   It has an email notifier which uses Velocity for formatting the
    notification emails.
    </td>
   </tr>

   <tr>
    <td>
     <a href="http://eyebrowse.tigris.org/">Eyebrowse</a>
    </td>
    <td>
        Eyebrowse is a Java Servlet browser for
        Unix mbox format mail archives.
    </td>
   </tr>

   <tr>
    <td>
     <a href="http://www.vamphq.com/hazel.html">
     Hazel</a>
    </td>
    <td>
    Hazel is a Web Start/JNLP app catalog creator (jnlp2html).
    Hazel allows you to create your own Web Start/JNLP app catalogs.
    Hazel extracts all JNLP links from HTML documents and creates an
    informative, neat looking HTML document listing all WebStart/JNLP apps.
    Hazel uses Velocity as its template engine.
    </td>
   </tr>

    <tr>
    <td>
     <a href="http://xjr.sourceforge.net/">XJR : XML to Java via Reflection API</a>
    </td>
    <td>
        Project toolkit for XML &lt;-&gt; Java compilation and mapping.
        Among other things, compiles DTDs to Java class hierarchies.
        Will create XML documents from those hierarchies and others...
    </td>
   </tr>

    <tr>
    <td>
  <a href="http://velocidoc.sourceforge.net/intro.html">Velocidoc</a>
    </td>
    <td>
    Velocidoc is a Velocimacro documentation tool modeled after
    Javadoc that allows you to generate HTML documentation for your
    Velocimacro libraries.
    </td>
   </tr>

    <tr>
    <td>
  <a href="http://scarab.tigris.org/">Scarab</a>
    </td>
    <td>
    Scarab is an Issue/Artiface tracking system that has been developed
    on top of Velocity and Turbine and is available under an open source
    license.
    </td>
   </tr>

   <tr>
    <td>
  <a href="http://luxor-xul.sourceforge.net">Luxor</a>
    </td>
    <td>
    Luxor is an open-source XML User Interface Language (XUL) toolkit for
    building rich cross-platform, zero-admin desktop apps in Java. Luxor
    supports hand-picked Mozilla XUL goodies and also includes a ultra
    light-weight, multi-threaded web server, a portal engine, and Velocity
    as its template engine.
    </td>
   </tr>

   <tr>
    <td>
  <a href="http://www.beardediris.com/webkiosk.html">WebAmortize</a>
    </td>
    <td>
    WebAmortization is a simple Java servlet that implements an
    online calculator for computing mortgage payments using the Velocity
    template engine.
    </td>
   </tr>

   <tr>
    <td>
      <a href="http://dione.zcu.cz/~toman40/ActionPack/">Action Pack</a>
    </td>
    <td>
    ActionPack is a distribution of independent,
    but cooperating, opensource modules for web applications development.
    </td>
   </tr>

   <tr>
    <td>
      <a href="http://www.jeewiz.co.uk/index.html">
      JeeWiz : Enterprise System Builder</a>
    </td>
    <td>
    JeeWiz! uses templates to generate J2EE infrastructure code,
    deployment descriptors and build jobs. The result is good news
    for everyone on a J2EE project.
    </td>
   </tr>

   <tr>
     <td>
       <a href="http://vdoclet.sourceforge.net/">vDoclet</a>
     </td>
     <td>
       vDoclet is a Javadoc-based code-generation framework. It takes Java
       source-code, annotated with custom Javadoc tags, and uses Velocity
       templates to produce a number of output files.  Templates are
       included for generating various EJB-related components.
    </td>
  </tr>

   <tr>
    <td>
     <a href="ftp://ftp.rexursive.com/pub/pump/pump.tar.gz">Pump Servlet</a>
    </td>
    <td>
       Bojan Smojver's PumpServlet is an
       alternative to the core VelocityServlet to use as a baseclass for
       developing Velocity-powered servlets.  See the documentation included
       in the download for more information. (That should motivate Bojan...)
    </td>
   </tr>

   <tr>
    <td>
     <a href="http://edencrm.sf.net">EdenCRM</a>
    </td>
    <td>
        EdenCRM is an open source java application for Customer Relationship
        Management which is designed specifically for small businesses.
        It runs on the desktop and does not require any server software
        (unless you want to have multiple users use a shared database for
        tickets and history entries).
    </td>
   </tr>

   <tr>
    <td>
     <a href="http://boss.bekk.no/boss/middlegen/">Middlegen</a>
    </td>
    <td>
     Middlegen is a code generation tool for EJB 2.0 CMP/CMR Entity Beans.
     It's useful if you have a database with existing tables and you want to
     map the tables to Entity Beans. You don't want to write a lot of code.
     You want the code to be generated. The code generated by Middlegen relies
     on further processing by XDoclet to produce even more code
     (home/remote/local interfaces, primary key classes and deployment descriptors).
    </td>
   </tr>

   <tr>
    <td>
     <a href="http://www.rollerweblogger.org/">Roller Weblogger</a>
    </td>
    <td>
       Roller is server-based weblogging software - a web application -
       that is designed to support multiple simultaneous weblog users and
       visitors.
    </td>
   </tr>

   <tr>
    <td>
     <a href="http://www.aidministrator.nl/spectacle/">Spectacle:Server</a>
    </td>
    <td>
	Spectacle Server is a 100% Java web component (to be deployed in
	a web app server like Tomcat/JBoss/SunOne/WebSphere) which offers
	high-performance, scalable guided exploration on sets of structured or
	unstructured data. Spectacle uses Velocity templates for the rendering of 
	information objects in HTML, XML or other formats.
    </td>
   </tr>

     <tr>
      <td>
       <a href="http://www.cotsec.com/">Cotsec Forms</a>
      </td>
      <td>
          Cotsec Forms is a framework for generating Forms based applications
      </td>
     </tr>

     <tr>
      <td>
       <a href="http://jag.sourceforge.net/">JAG - Java Application Generator</a>
      </td>
      <td>
        JAG is an application that creates complete, working J2EE applications.
          It is intended to alleviate much of the repetitive work involved in
          creating such applications, while providing a means of quality
          assurance that the applications created will be of consistent quality.
      </td>
     </tr>

 </table>

 </section>

 <section name="Velocity powered Websites">
 <p>
  This is a list of public web sites that are created using Velocity.
  This, of course, is by no means a complete listing of all of the
  Velocity powered websites.
 </p>

 <p>
  Currently, in the Jakarta project, the main Jakarta website, Velocity,
  Ant, ECS, James, Jetspeed, Log4J, JMeter, Regexp, Tomcat, Turbine,
  Commons, and Alexandria projects are all rendered as static HTML using
  Velocity through the use of the Anakia XML transformation tool.
 </p>

 <p>
  If you want your Velocity powered site listed here, please post a message on
  the Velocity user
  <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/site/mail.html">mailing list</a>.
 </p>

 <table>
   <tr>
    <td><b>URL</b></td>
    <td><b>Description</b></td>
    <td><b>Created By</b></td>
   </tr>

   <tr>
    <td>
     <a href="http://tambora.zenplex.org">tambora.zenplex.org</a>
    </td>
    <td>
     Home of an OSS project.
    </td>
    <td>
     <a href="http://www.zenplex.org">Zenplex</a>
    </td>
   </tr>

   <tr>
    <td>
     <a href="http://www.flashcan.com">www.flashcan.com</a>
    </td>
    <td>
     An interactive card making game using Velocity, Turbine and
     Macromedia's Flash5.
    </td>
    <td>
     <a href="http://www.zincroe.com">ZincRoe</a>
    </td>
   </tr>

   <tr>
    <td>
     <a href="http://www.tigris.org">www.tigris.org</a>
    </td>
    <td>
     Open source development tool suite.
    </td>
    <td>
     <a href="http://www.collab.net">CollabNet</a>
    </td>
   </tr>

   <tr>
    <td>
     <a href="http://www.devicetop.com">www.devicetop.com</a>
    </td>
    <td>
     Devicetop.com is an industry-sponsored online community for
     developers of Java-based applications for smart Internet devices.
    </td>
    <td>
     <a href="http://www.espial.com">Espial</a>
    </td>
   </tr>

   <tr>
    <td>
     <a href="http://www.adeptra.com">www.adeptra.com</a>
    </td>
    <td>
     Adeptra is a venture-backed private company that provides
     2-way alterting solutions for personal electronic devices.
    </td>
    <td>
     <a href="http://www.adeptra.com">Adeptra Inc.</a>
    </td>
   </tr>

   <tr>
    <td>
     <a href="http://www.discuss.gr">www.discuss.gr</a>
    </td>
    <td>
     Online discussion forum site built using Turbine and Velocity.
    </td>
    <td>
    </td>
   </tr>

   <tr>
    <td>
     <a href="http://www.webhelp.com/">www.webhelp.com</a>
    </td>
    <td>
      Webhelp is a company that provides distributed call center integration
      software and services for web and wireless technologies.  WebHelp
      incorporated Velocity with their ETranscript component, so that events
      generated in a conference are rendered as MIME email and XML using Velocity
      templates.
    </td>
    <td>
     <a href="http://www.webhelp.com">WebHelp</a>
    </td>
   </tr>

   <tr>
    <td>
     <a href="http://www.goodwoodinteriors.com">www.goodwoodinteriors.com</a>
    </td>
    <td>
     Wood furniture factory site.  The static content of this site is
     generated using Velocity templates, providing the benefit of simple
     deployment without the overhead of an online servlet container and
     database with the advantage of Velocity's ease of use for generating
     data driven content.
    </td>
    <td>
     <a href="http://www.jawasoft.com">P.T.Jawasoft</a>
    </td>
   </tr>

  <tr>
    <td>
     <a href="http://www.freebok.net/">www.freebok.net</a>
    </td>
    <td>
      Freebok.net is a free guestbook service that uses Velocity
      templates for the site. More importantly the guestbook users
      have the option to create their own Velocity templates to
      render the layout of their guestbook.
    </td>
    <td>
     <a href="http://www.freebok.net/">Freebok.net</a>
    </td>
   </tr>

  <tr>
    <td>
     <a href="http://www.studioz.tv/">www.studioz.tv</a>
    </td>
    <td>
     StudioZ is an events space in San Francisco where artists of all
     types can promote their own events. We use Anakia with a custom
     style.vsl to generate the entire static website XML->HTML in a
     matter of seconds.
    </td>
    <td>
     <a href="http://www.whichever.com/">www.whichever.com</a>
    </td>
   </tr>

   <tr>
    <td>
     <a href="http://www.cbc.ca/olympics/">www.cbc.ca/olympics/</a>
    </td>
    <td>
    The Canadian Broadcasting Corporation's 2002 Winter Olympic
    website was developed using Velocity.
    </td>
    <td>
     <a href="http://www.cbc.ca/">Canadian Broadcasting Corporation</a>
    </td>
   </tr>

   <tr>
    <td>
     <a href="http://www.salutebenessere.tv/">www.salutebenessere.tv</a>
    </td>
    <td>
    SaluteBenessere Channel is a free Italian satellite TV channel dedicated to
    well-being, sports and medicine. It is possible to watch the channel live on
    Internet through a Real streaming server.
    </td>
    <td>
     <a href="http://www.aliasmedia.it/">Alias Media</a>
    </td>
   </tr>

   <tr>
    <td>
     <a href="http://www.impress.com/">www.IMPRESS.com</a>
    </td>
    <td>
    Anakia-generated corporate site for Impress Software AG, producer of
    integration products and services.
    </td>
    <td>
     <a href="http://www.impress.com/">Impress Software AG</a>
    </td>
   </tr>

   <tr>
    <td>
     <a href="http://www.davinci-learn.com/">www.davinci-learn.com</a>
    </td>
    <td>
     DaVinci provides innovative web-based solutions for testing, course
    material delivery, and learning content management.
    </td>
    <td>
     <a href="http://www.base2.cc/">Base2 Corporation</a>
    </td>
   </tr>

   <tr>
    <td>
     <a href="http://www.bkfev.de/">www.bkfev.de</a>
    </td>
    <td>
      Site of a German Birman Cats owners association.
      Static site generated with Velocity.
    </td>
    <td>
     <a href="http://www.bkfev.de/">Birmakatzenfreunden</a>
    </td>
   </tr>
  </table>
 </section>

<section name="Frameworks that support Velocity">
 <p>
  This is a list of web frameworks that include support for
  Velocity 'out of the box'.  While many web frameworks are
  being used with Velocity, such as the
  <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/struts/">Jakarta Struts</a>
  project, the following include support for Velocity within the
  package.
 </p>

 <p>
  If you want your Velocity-powered framework listed here, please post a message on
  the Velocity user
  <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/site/mail.html">mailing list</a>.
 </p>

 <table>
   <tr>
    <td><b>Name</b></td>
    <td><b>Description</b></td>
   </tr>

   <tr>
    <td>
     <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/turbine/">Jakarta Turbine</a>
    </td>
    <td>
     One of the early servlet-based web frameworks, and currently in version 2.1,
     Turbine is a framework that allows experienced
     Java developers to quickly build secure web applications.  While Turbines
     primary templating technology is Velocity, it also supports JSP, WebMacro,
     FreeMarker, ECS and others.
    </td>
   </tr>

   <tr>
    <td></td>
    <td></td>
   </tr>

   <tr>
    <td>
     <a href="http://www.melati.org">Melati</a>
    </td>
    <td>
     Melati is a tool for building Java-programmed websites backed by a database.
    </td>
   </tr>

   <tr>
    <td>
     <a href=" http://www.jpublish.org/">JPublish</a>
    </td>
    <td>
     JPublish is a web publishing framework which merges the Velocity template engine
     with a content repository and application control framework.
    </td>
   </tr>

 <tr>
    <td>
     <a href="http://mav.sourceforge.net">Maverick</a>
    </td>
    <td>
    Maverick is a Model-View-Controller framework for publishing web applications.
    It is a simple, minimalist framework which offers the ability to render views
    with JSP, Velocity, or XSLT directly.
    </td>
   </tr>

    <tr>
    <td>
     <a href="http://sourceforge.net/projects/webwork/">WebWork</a>
    </td>
    <td>
    WebWork is a web application framework for J2EE. It is based on a
    concept called "Pull HMVC" (Pull Hierarchical Model View Controller).
    The basic idea is to separate the site programmers' and site designers'
    tasks.  WebWork now supports Velocity with their 1.0 release.
    </td>
   </tr>

    <tr>
    <td>
     <a href="http://www.niggle.org/">Niggle</a>
    </td>
    <td>
    Niggle is a Java class library intended
    for use in development of robust, maintainable web applications.
    The Niggle framework is designed to alleviate the repetitive,
    tedious details typical of those kinds of applications
    </td>
   </tr>

    <tr>
    <td>
     <a href="http://dione.zcu.cz/~toman40/ActionServlet">ActionServlet</a>
    </td>
    <td>
    ActionServlet provides an easy mapping of user actions (HTTP requests)
    to methods of Java components together with automatic conversion of
    HTTP parameters to the values of Java types.
    </td>
   </tr>

  </table>
 </section>


 </body>
</document>

