<?xml version="1.0"?>

<document>
 <properties>
  <title>Velocity powered Websites</title>
  <author email="jon@latchkey.com">Jon S. Stevens</author>
 </properties>

 <body>

 <section name="Powered-By Velocity Logo">
 
 <p>
   This is not a requirement, but we would love it if you would adopt
   our Powered-By Velocity logo for your own website in order to show
   your support for our hard work.
 </p>
 
 <p>
 <img src="images/powered-by-logo.gif" alt="Powered By Velocity" width="77" height="32" />
 </p>

 </section>
 
 <section name="Velocity-powered Products">
 <p>
   Velocity is a utility tool which can be used in conjunction with
   general applications which may or may not be web based.
 </p>

 <table>
   <tr>
    <td><b>Name</b></td>
    <td><b>Description</b></td>
   </tr>

   <tr>
    <td>
     <a href="http://www.gentleware.com/products/index.php3">GentleWare</a> Poseidon for UML
    </td>
    <td>
     GentleWare's Poseidon product uses Velocity as a template tool in
     order to generate Java code from UML diagrams that you design using
     their tool.
    </td>
   </tr>

   <tr>
    <td>
     <a href="http://www.xadra.com/products/vas/index.html">Xadra</a> VelocityAdaptorServer
    </td>
    <td>
     The VelocityAdaptorServer is a very simple yet extremely flexible
     system for the creation of HTML-based Java Management
     Extensions[tm] (JMX) compatible management consoles.
    </td>
   </tr>

   <tr>
    <td>
     <a href="http://www.geocities.com/vamp201/index.html">Venus Application Publisher (Vamp)</a>
    </td>
    <td>
      Venus Application Publisher is a user-friendly tool that helps you
      package, sign and publish Java (TM) Network Launching Protocol
      (JNLP) software.
    </td>
   </tr>

  <tr>
    <td>
     <a href="http://jtop.sourceforge.net/">J/Top</a>
    </td>
    <td>
    J/Top is an open source application for monitoring multiple servers running
    'top'.   It has an email notifier which uses Velocity for formatting the 
    notification emails.
    </td>
   </tr>

 </table>
 
 </section>

 <section name="Velocity powered Websites">
 <p>
  This is a list of public web sites that are created using Velocity.
  This, of course, is by no means a complete listing of all of the
  Velocity powered websites.
 </p>

 <p>
  Currently, in the Jakarta project, the main Jakarta website, Velocity,
  Ant, ECS, James, Jetspeed, Log4J, JMeter, Regexp, Tomcat, Turbine,
  Commons, and Alexandria projects are all rendered as static HTML using
  Velocity through the use of the Anakia XML transformation tool.
 </p>

 <p>
  If you want your Velocity powered site listed here, please post a message on
  the Velocity user
  <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/site/mail.html">mailing list</a>.
 </p>

 <table>
   <tr>
    <td><b>URL</b></td>
    <td><b>Description</b></td>
    <td><b>Created By</b></td>
   </tr>

   <tr>
    <td>
     <a href="http://tambora.zenplex.org">tambora.zenplex.org</a>
    </td>
    <td>
     Home of an OSS project.
    </td>
    <td>
     <a href="http://www.zenplex.org">Zenplex</a>
    </td>
   </tr>

   <tr>
    <td>
     <a href="http://www.flashcan.com">www.flashcan.com</a>
    </td>
    <td>
     An interactive card making game using Velocity, Turbine and
     Macromedia's Flash5.
    </td>
    <td>
     <a href="http://www.zincroe.com">ZincRoe</a>
    </td>
   </tr>

   <tr>
    <td>
     <a href="http://www.tigris.org">www.tigris.org</a>
    </td>
    <td>
     Open source development tool suite.
    </td>
    <td>
     <a href="http://www.collab.net">CollabNet</a>
    </td>
   </tr>

   <tr>
    <td>
     <a href="http://www.devicetop.com">www.devicetop.com</a>
    </td>
    <td>
     Devicetop.com is an industry-sponsored online community for
     developers of Java-based applications for smart Internet devices.
    </td>
    <td>
     <a href="http://www.espial.com">Espial</a>
    </td>
   </tr>

   <tr>
    <td>
     <a href="http://www.adeptra.com">www.adeptra.com</a>
    </td>
    <td>
     Adeptra is a venture-backed private company that provides
     2-way alterting solutions for personal electronic devices.
    </td>
    <td>
     <a href="http://www.adeptra.com">Adeptra Inc.</a>
    </td>
   </tr>

   <tr>
    <td>
     <a href="http://www.discuss.gr">www.discuss.gr</a>
    </td>
    <td>
     Online discussion forum site built using Turbine and Velocity.
    </td>
    <td>
    </td>
   </tr>

  </table>
 </section>

<section name="Frameworks that support Velocity">
 <p>
  This is a list of web frameworks that include support for 
  Velocity 'out of the box'.  While many web frameworks are
  being used with Velocity, such as the 
  <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/struts/">Jakarta Struts</a>
  project, the following include support for Velocity within the
  package.
 </p>

 <p>
  If you want your Velocity-powered framework listed here, please post a message on
  the Velocity user
  <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/site/mail.html">mailing list</a>.
 </p>

 <table>
   <tr>
    <td><b>Name</b></td>
    <td><b>Description</b></td>
   </tr>

   <tr>
    <td>
     <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/turbine/">Jakarta Turbine</a>
    </td>
    <td>
     One of the early servlet-based web frameworks, and currently in version 2.1,
     Turbine is a framework that allows experienced 
     Java developers to quickly build secure web applications.  While Turbines
     primary templating technology is Velocity, it also supports JSP, WebMacro,
     FreeMarker, ECS and others.
    </td>
   </tr>

   <tr>
    <td></td>
    <td></td>
   </tr>

   <tr>
    <td>
     <a href="http://www.melati.org">Melati</a>
    </td>
    <td>
     Melati is a tool for building Java-programmed websites backed by a database.
    </td>
   </tr>

   <tr>
    <td>
     <a href="http://jpublish.sourceforge.net/">JPublish</a>
    </td>
    <td>
     JPublish is a web publishing framework which merges the Velocity template engine 
     with a content repository and application control framework.
    </td>
   </tr>

 <tr>
    <td>
     <a href="http://mav.sourceforge.net">Maverick</a>
    </td>
    <td>
    Maverick is a Model-View-Controller framework for publishing web applications. 
    It is a simple, minimalist framework which offers the ability to render views 
    with JSP, Velocity, or XSLT directly. 
    </td>
   </tr>
  
    <tr>
    <td>
     <a href="http://sourceforge.net/projects/webwork/">WebWork</a>
    </td>
    <td>
    WebWork is a web application framework for J2EE. It is based on a 
    concept called "Pull HMVC" (Pull Hierarchical Model View Controller). 
    The basic idea is to separate the site programmers' and site designers' 
    tasks.  WebWork now supports Velocity with their 1.0 release (currently
    in Release Candidate 1).
    </td>
   </tr>


  </table>
 </section>

 </body>
</document>

