<?xml version="1.0"?>

<document>

 <header>
  <title>Velocity User Guide</title>
  <subtitle>Velocity User Guide</subtitle>
  <authors>
   <person name="Velocity Documentation Team" email="jvanzyl@locus.apache.org"/>
   <person name="John Castura" email="jcastura@compusense.com"/>
  </authors>
 </header>

<body>

 <s1 title="About this Guide">

 <p>
    The Velocity User Guide is intended to help page designers and content 
    providers get aquainted with Velocity and the syntax of its simple yet 
    powerful scripting language, the Velocity Template Language (VTL). 
    Many of the examples in this guide deal with using Velocity to embed 
    dynamic content in web sites, but all VTL examples are equally applicable 
    to other pages and templates.
 </p> 

 </s1>

 <s1 title="What is Velocity?">
 
 <p>
    Velocity is a Java-based template engine. It permits web page designers
    to reference methods defined in Java code. Web designers can work in parallel 
    with Java programmers to develop web sites according to the Model-View-Controller
    (MVC) model, meaning that web page designers can focus solely on creating
    a well-designed site, and programmers can focus solely on writing
    top-notch code. Velocity separates Java code from the web pages,
    making the web site more maintainable over the long run and providing
    a viable alternative to
    <link href="http://java.sun.com/products/jsp/">Java Server Pages</link>
    (JSPs) or <link href="http://www.php.net/">PHP</link>.
 </p>
 
 <p>
    Velocity can be used to generate web pages, SQL, PostScript and other 
    output from templates.
    It can be used either as a standalone utility for generating
    source code and reports, or as an integrated component of other systems.
    When complete, Velocity will provide template services for the
    <link href="http://java.apache.org/turbine/">Turbine</link>
    web application framework. Velocity-Turbine will provide
    a template service that will allow web applications to be developed
    according to a true MVC model.
 </p>
 
 </s1>

 <s1 title="What can Velocity do for me?">

   <s1 title="The Mud Store Example">

   <p>
    Suppose you have an online store that specializes in selling mud. Let's call
    it "The Online Mud Store". Business is thriving. Your customers 
    place orders for various types and quantities of mud. They
    login to your site using their username and password, which allows them to 
    view their orders and buy more mud. Right now, Terracotta Mud is on sale, which
    is very popular. A minority of your customers regularly buy Bright Red 
    Mud, which is also on sale, though not as popular and usually relegated 
    to the margin of your web page. Information about each customer is tracked
    in your database, so it occurs to you one day, Why not use Velocity to target
    special deals on mud to the customers who are most interested in those types of 
    mud?
   </p>
 
   <p>
    Velocity makes it easy to customize web pages to your online visitors. As a web site 
    designer at The Mud Room, you want to make the web page that the customer will 
    see after logging into your site.
   </p>
 
   <p>
    You meet with software engineers at your company, and everyone
    has agreed that the variable <pre>$customer</pre> will hold information
    pertaining to the customer currently logged in,
    that <pre>$mudsOnSpecial</pre> will be all the types mud on sale at present.
    The <pre>$flogger</pre> object contains methods that help with promotion.
    For the task at hand, let's concern ourselves only with these three 
    variables. Remember, you don't need to worry about how the software 
    engineers extract the necessary information from the database, you just need
    to know that it works. This lets you get on with your job, and lets the
    software engineers get on with theirs.
   </p>
 
   <p>
    You could embed the following VTL statement in the web page:
   </p>
 
   <p>
    <source><![CDATA[
    <HTML>
    <BODY>
    Hello $customer.Name!
    <table>
    #foreach ($mud in $mudsOnSpecial)
       #if ($customer.hasPurchased($mud))
          <tr>
            <td>
              $flogger.getPromo($mud)
            </td>
          </tr>
       #end
    #end
    </table>
    ]]></source>
   </p>
 
   <p>
    The extact details of the <pre>foreach</pre> statement will be described
    in greater depth shortly; what's important is the impact this short 
    script will have on your web site. When a customer with a 
    penchant for Bright Red Mud logs in, and Bright Red Mud
    is on sale, that is what this customer will see, prominently displayed. 
    If another customer with a long history of Terracotta Mud purchases logs in,
    the notice of a Terracotta Mud sale will be front and center. 
    The flexibility of Velocity is enormous and limited only by your creativity.
   </p>
 
   </s1>

   <p>
    VTL has many other elements documented in the VTL Reference, which collectively 
    give you the power and flexibility you need to make your web site a web
    <em>presence</em>. As you get more familiar with these elements, you will begin to unleash the power
    of Velocity.
   </p>

 </s1>

 <s1 title="Velocity Template Language (VTL): An Introduction">

 <p>
    The Velocity Template 
    Language (VTL) is meant to provide the easiest, simplest, and cleanest way 
    to incorporate dynamic content in a web page. Even a web page developer with little 
    or no programming experience should soon be capable of using VTL to incorporate 
    dynamic content in a web site.
 </p>

 <p>
    VTL uses <em>statements</em> to embed dynamic content in a web site. Statements 
    are made up of <em>elements</em>. Here is an example of a VTL statement
    embedded in an HTML document:
 </p>
 
 <p>
    <source><![CDATA[
    #set $a = "Velocity"
    ]]>
    </source>
 </p>

 <p>
    This VTL statement, like all VTL statements that contain directives, begins 
    with the <pre>#</pre> character. When an online visitor requests 
    your web page, the 
    Velocity Templating Engine will search through your web page to find all
    <pre>#</pre> characters, then determine which mark the beginning of VTL 
    statements, and which of the # characters that have nothing to do with VTL.
 </p>

 <p>
    The <pre>#</pre> character is followed by a directive,
    <pre>set</pre>. The <pre>set</pre> directive works in conjunction with other
    script elements to assign a <em>value</em> to a <em>variable</em>. The variable 
    is listed on the left and its value on the right; the two are separated by an 
    <pre>=</pre> character.
 </p>
 
 <p>
    In the example above, the variable is <pre>$a</pre> and the value is
    <pre>Velocity</pre>. Variables <em>always</em> begin with <pre>$</pre> characters. 
    Values are always enclosed in quotes; with Velocity there is no confusion about
    data types, as only strings (text-based information) may be passed to variables.
 </p>

 <p>
    Once a value has been assigned to a variable, you can reference the 
    variable anywhere in your HTML document. In the following example, 
    a value is assigned to <pre>$foo</pre> and later referenced.
 </p>

 <p>
    <source><![CDATA[
    <HTML>
    <BODY>
    #set $foo = "Velocity"
    Hello $foo World!
    </BODY>
    <HTML>
    ]]>
    </source>
 </p>

 <p>
    The result is a web page that prints "Hello Velocity World!".
 </p>

 <p>   
    To make your VTL directive statements more readable, we encourage you to 
    start each VTL statement on a new line, although you are not required to 
    do so. The <pre>set</pre> directive will be revisited in greater detail 
    later on.
 </p>

 <p>
    The <pre>set</pre> example is useful for demonstrating the syntax of a simple VTL 
    statement, but not very exciting for revealing the capabilities of Velocity.
 </p>


 </s1>

 <s1 title="VTL Reference">
    
    <p>
    Velocity references its variables in a fashion similar to 
    <link href="http://www.perl.com">Perl</link> (i.e. they 
    use a <pre>$</pre>), but takes advantage of some Java principles that 
    template designers will find easy to use. For example:
    </p>

    <p>
    <source><![CDATA[
    $foo
    $foo.getBar() or $foo.Bar
    $data.getUser("jon") or $data.User("jon")
    $data.getRequest().getServerName() or $data.Request.ServerName
    ]]></source>
    </p>

    <p>
    These examples illustrate alternative uses for the same variables. 
    Velocity takes advantage of Java's introspection and 
    bean features to resolve the variable names to both objects in the Context 
    as well as the objects methods. It is possible to embed and evaluate 
    variables almost anywhere in your template.
    </p>
    
    <p>
    Everything coming to and from a variable is treated as a String object. 
    If there is an object that represents $foo (such as an Integer object), 
    then Velocity will call its .toString() method to resolve the 
    object into a String.
    </p>

    <s1 title="Variables">

    <p>
    VTL variables can reference three types of objects: variables, 
    properties, and methods. 
    
    <s1 title="Variables">
    
    <p>
    A VTL variable, such as <pre>$foo</pre>, can get its value from 
    either a <pre>set</pre> directive in the template, or from the
    Java code. For example, if the Java variable <pre>$foo</pre>
    has the value <pre>bar</pre> at the time the template is requested,
    <pre>bar</pre> replaces all instances of <pre>$foo</pre> on the web 
    page. Alternatively, if I include the statement
    </p>
    
    <p>
    <source><![CDATA[
    #set $foo = "bar"
    ]]></source>
    </p>
    
    <p>
    the output will be the same for all instances of <pre>$foo</pre>
    that follow this directive.
    </p>
    
    </s1>
    
    <s1 title="Properties">
    
    <p>
    The second flavour of VTL variable references properties, and it has
    a distinctive format:
    </p>
    
    <p>
    <source><![CDATA[
    $whomever.Address
    ]]></source>
    </p>
    
    <p>
    Here, <pre>$whomever.Address</pre> can have two meanings. It can mean,
    Look in the hashtable identified as <pre>whomever</pre> and return the
    value associated with the key <pre>Address</pre>. This syntax can also 
    be referring to a method (variables that refer to methods will be discussed
    in the next section); <pre>$whomever.Address</pre> could be an 
    abbreviated way of writing <pre>getAddress("whomever")</pre>. 
    When your page is requested, Velocity will determine which of these 
    two possibilities makes sense, and then return the appropriate value.
    </p>
    
    </s1>
    
    <s1 title="Methods">
    
    <p>
    A method is defined in the Java code and is capable of doing something
    useful, like running a calculation or arriving at a decision. VTL 
    variables that refer to Java methods have the following format:
    </p>
    
    <p>
    <source><![CDATA[
    $purchase.getTotalPrice()
    ]]></source>
    </p>
    
    <p>
    In this example, the getTotalPrice() method, defined in the Java code, 
    will presumably return the total price of a purchase that is being tracked.
    Note that this could also have been written,
    <pre>$purchase.TotalPrice</pre>.
    </p>
    
    </s1>
    </p>
  </s1>

    <s1 title="Conditionals">

    <s1 title="If / ElseIf / Else Conditionals">
    <p>
    The #if statement in Velocity allows for text in the brackets to be 
    included in the text, on the conditional that the if statement
    is true. For example:
    </p>

    <p>
    <source><![CDATA[
    #if ($foo)
        <strong>Velocity Rocks!</strong>
    #end
    ]]></source>
    </p>

    <p>
    The variable $foo is evaluated to see if it is a boolean or not null; the 
    content within the brackets becomes the output if the evaluation is true. 
    Unlike in JSP, Velocity does not force web developers to wrap HTML code 
    within an out.println(), or to delve into ugly workarounds to out.println().
    </p>
    
    <p>
    An #elseif or #else element can be used with an #if element.
    </p>

    <p>
    <source><![CDATA[
    #if ($foo)
        <strong>Velocity Rocks!</strong>
    #elseif($bar)
        <strong>Velocity Rocks Again!</strong>
    #else
        <strong>Velocity Still Rocks!</strong>
    #end
    ]]></source>
    </p>
    
    <p>
    In this example, if $foo is false, then the output will be
    <strong>Velocity Still Rocks!</strong> 
    </p>

    <p>
    Note that logical operators are not yet available in Velocity. 
    This functionality is expected to be added soon. An example of
    a logical operator is shown below.
    </p>

    <p>
    <source><![CDATA[
    #if ($foo && $bar)
        <strong>Velocity Rocks!</strong>
    #end
    ]]></source>
    </p>
    </s1>
</s1>

<s1 title="Loops">
    <s1 title="Foreach Loop">
    <p>
    The #foreach element allows for looping. For example:
    </p>

    <p>
    <source><![CDATA[
    <ul>
    #foreach ($product in $allProducts)
        <li>$product</li>
    #end
    </ul>
    ]]></source>
    </p>

    <p>
    This #foreach loop causes the $allProducts list (the object) to be 
    looped over for all of the products (targets) in the list. Each time 
    through the loop, the value from $allProducts is placed into the 
    $product variable.
    </p>
    
    <p>
    The contents of the $allProducts variable is either a Vector, a Hashtable 
    or an Array. The value assigned to the $product variable is a Java
    Object and can be referenced from a variable as such. For example, if 
    $product was really a Product class in Java, its name could be retrieved
    by referencing the $product.Name method (ie: Product.getName()).
    </p>
    </s1>
</s1>    

<s1 title="Include">
    <p>
    The #include script element allows the template designer to import a 
    local file, which is then inserted into the location where the #include 
    directive is defined. The contents of the file are not rendered through 
    the template engine.
    </p>
    
    <p>
    <source><![CDATA[
    #include /path/to/file.vm
    ]]></source>
    </p>
</s1>

<s1 title="Set">
    <p>
    The #set script element allows the template designer to set variables 
    within the Context.
    </p>
    
    <p>
    <source><![CDATA[
    #set $name = "Fred"
    ]]></source>
    </p>
    
    <p>
    When using the #set directive, the variable on the left side must be 
    prefixed with a $. This provides a 
    consistent syntax for referencing variables in Velocity.
    </p>
    
    <p>
    The following script elements have not been implemented.
    </p>
</s1>

<s1 title="Comments">
    <p>
    There are three comment types that allow the template designer to 
    place descriptive text in templates that is not placed into the
    output of the template engine.
    </p>
    
    <p>
    <source><![CDATA[
    ## this is a line comment
    ]]></source>
    </p>

    <p>
    <source><![CDATA[
    #*
    
    This is a multiline
    block comment used for
    longer descriptions.
    
    *#
    ]]></source>
    </p>

    <p>
    <source><![CDATA[
    #** 
    
    This is a VTL comment block and
    may be used to store such information 
    as the document author and versioning
    information:
    
    @author 
    @version 5
    
    *#
    ]]></source>
    </p>

</s1>

<s1 title="Stop">
    <p>
    The #stop script element allows the template designer to stop the execution
    of the template engine and return. This is useful for debugging purposes.
    </p>
    
    <p>
    <source><![CDATA[
    #stop
    ]]></source>
    </p>    
</s1>

<s1 title="Macro">
    <p>
    With the #macro script element, the template designer can define a 
    time-saving macro. 
    </p>    
    
    <p>
    <source><![CDATA[
    #macro (row $content) <tr><td>$content</td></tr> #end
    ]]></source>
    </p>
    
    <p>
    This establishes a macro called "row", which uses HTML tags to
    put content into its own table data cell in an HTML table. Having 
    defined the #row macro, the template designer can now call the #row 
    macro by name.
    </p>
    
    <p>
    <source><![CDATA[
    <table>
    #foreach ($element in $list)
	#row ($element)
    #end
    </table>
    ]]></source>
    </p>
    
    <p>
    Here a newly created #row macro is nested inside a #foreach
    statement. As the #foreach statement loops through each $element
    target in the $list object, the #row macro will take the value of
    $element and put it into its table data cell.
    </p>
    
</s1>

</s1>

</body>
</document>
