<?xml version="1.0"?>

<!--
   Copyright 2000-2004 The Apache Software Foundation

   Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
   you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
   You may obtain a copy of the License at

       http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

   Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
   distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
   WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
   See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
   limitations under the License.
-->


<document>

 <properties>
  <title>The Velocity JSP Tag Library</title>
  <author email="geirm@apache.org">Geir Magnusson Jr.</author>
 </properties>

<body>

<section name="Contents">

<ol>
<li>
<a href="#So You Have To Use JSP...">So You Have To Use JSP...</a>
<ul>
  <li>
    <a href="#What Are The Advantages">What Are The Advantages?</a>
  </li>
</ul>
</li>

<li>
 <a href="#Using The Velocity Taglib">Using The Velocity Taglib</a>
 <ul>
  <li>
    <a href="#Automatic Scope Access">Automatic Scope Access</a>
  </li>
  <li>
    <a href="#Strict Scope Access">Strict Scope Access</a>
  </li>
</ul>
</li>

<li>
<a href="#Building The Velocity Taglib">Building The Velocity Taglib</a>
<ul>
  <li>
    <a href="#JJAR build">Build Using JJAR</a>
  </li>
  <li>
    <a href="#nonJJAR build">Non-JJAR Traditional Build</a>
  </li>
</ul>
</li>

<li>
<a href="#Configuration">Configuration</a>
</li>
</ol>

</section>

<section name="So You Have To Use JSP...">

<p>
 Sometimes it appears you don't have a choice - technology decisions are 
 made based on all sorts of factors, ranging from network externalities
("They're using it - I should too...") to legacy considerations
("They used it - I have to...").
</p>

<p>
In the event where the usage of JSP is mandatory, we offer a JSP tag library that lets 
you take advantage of the simple control directives and powerful binding to the
Java object model offered by Velocity.  Using Velocity in your JSPs is as 
simple as :
</p>

<source><![CDATA[
<%@ taglib uri="/WEB-INF/veltag.tld" prefix="vel" %>

<html>
<head>
  <title> Velocity! </title>
</head>

<jsp:useBean id="mybean"  class="GeirBean" />

<body>
    <vel:velocity strictaccess="true">

         #set($mybean = $scopetool.getPageScope("mybean"))

         #if(true)
            this is true!
         #end

         <br>

         $mybean.string

         <br>

        #foreach($item in $mybean.array) 
            $item <br>
        #end

    </vel:velocity>
</body>
</html>
]]></source>

<p>
Not hard at all, is it?
</p>

<a name="What Are The Advantages"><strong>What Are The Advantages?</strong></a>

<p>
The first question asked when confronted with this subject is something 
along the lines of "What advantage does this have over 'pure' Velocity?".  
Generally, there are few reasons why one would take a Velocity-only 
system, and convert it to a JSP system with Velocity embedded in the 
JSP pages.  The only reason that you might want to do this is to use 
an existing JSP taglib that you want to use that you don't have the 
source code for, or don't wish to dig out the core functional classes 
of a taglib you do have the source for.  Otherwise, you could just drop
those core classes in the Context, and access them directly from within
the Velocity template.
</p>

<p>
The advantages, then, are found in a JSP-centric environment, where an
existing application is already written in JSP and you wish to add or
maintain functionality.  Some things that Velocity provides :
</p>

<ul>
<li> 
     Simple access to Java objects, without any need to create a taglib
     shell.  If it has public methods on a public interface, you can 
     drop it right into a scope and access directly (or use a tool to 
     create an instances of the class for you.)
</li>
<li> 
     Simple access to complicated Java objects.  It's not clear how to 
     access an arbitrary call chain such as $foo.bar( $thing ).getIterator().hasNext() 
     in JSP.
</li>
<li> 
     Although this is a matter of personal taste, some people prefer the
     control directives of Velocity ( #if(), #else(), #elseif(), #foreach() )
     to the various taglibs that offer the same functionality.
     <i>De gustibus non est disputandum!</i>.
</li>
<li> 
     An easy bridge between complicated Java objects and JSP - for example
     if you wished to dynamically choose/create an object at runtime, and
     then poke into a scope for access in other parts of the JSP, you could
     do that.
     <pre>
         &lt;vel:velocity strictaccess="true"&gt;
             #set($reqbean = $scopetool.getRequestScope("beaninrequest"))
             #set($newthing = $reqbean.getThing().makeBlue("azure"))
             $request.getSession().setAttribute("bluething", $newthing)
         &lt;/vel:velocity&gt;
     </pre>
     Or something like that :)
</li>
<li>
     If nothing else, there are always the Velocimacros.
</li>
</ul>

</section>

<section name="Using The Velocity Taglib">

<p>
The biggest challenge in bringing together Velocity and JSP is the 
'impedance matching' related to scope and bean access.  'Scope', 
the fundamental storage mechanism in JSP, is a 
concept that comes from the underlying servlet API, where data objects 
are stored for later retrieval within the page, request, session or
application.  Velocity organizes data in a non-hierachical mechanism 
called the 'context', the expectation being that a controller servlet
or other non-view code will manage and organize the data accessable 
to the template.
</p>

<p>
So to make data access in JSPs easy using the Velocity taglib, two 
separate approaches are offered.  These two approaches, automatic
access and strict access, allow two distinct ways of managing and 
accessing data.  These two ways can also be used together.
</p>

<a name="Automatic Scope Access"><strong>Automatic Scope Access</strong></a>

<p>
The first way, automatic access, is the most convenient.  When an 
object is referenced (via a VTL 'reference'), the scopes are searched
to find an object with the same id.  The scopes are searched in the 
order of :
</p>

<ol>
<li> page scope </li>
<li> request scope </li>
<li> session scope </li>
<li> application scope </li>
</ol>

<p> 
Automatic scope access is enabled by default.  To use 
automatic scope access, just access the bean by name. For example :
</p>

<source><![CDATA[
<!-- place a bean in page scope -->
<jsp:useBean id="mybean"  class="GeirBean" />

 <vel:velocity>

    <!-- just access by id - the context -->
    <!-- will find it automatically      -->

    #foreach($item in $mybean.array) 
       $item <br>
    #end

</vel:velocity>
]]></source>

<p>
While automatic scope access is the easier of the two methods, 
integrating with existing applications might require using the
other access mode, strict scope access, or a combination of the
two.
</p>

<a name="Strict Scope Access"><strong>Strict Scope Access</strong></a>
  <p>
   The alternative (or addition to) Automatic Scope Access is something called 
   <i>Strict Scope Access</i>.  Strict Scope Acccess means that the Velocity
   Context won't search the scopes for you - you must retrieve objects directly
   using ScopeTool that is provided for your use in the template.  This is a 
   closer model to that of regular JSP, where the designer must be aware of 
   the scopes that objects are stored in.
  </p>

   <p>
   For example, the following snippet of JSP shows how the scopetool is used to
   access an object in the request scope, and add it to the Velocity context.
   Note how the <code>strictaccess</code> property is set to true in the
   <code>&lt;vel:velocity strictaccess="true"&gt;</code> tag.  This tells 
   the Veltag taglib to not do any automatic scope searching.  Note that you can
   mix the two modes, leaving off (or setting to false) <code>strictaccess</code>
   and also using the scopetool to eliminate any question about the source
   of an object.
  </p>

<source><![CDATA[
<jsp:useBean id="beaninrequest" class="GeirBean" scope="request" />

<vel:velocity strictaccess="true">

         #set($reqbean = $scopetool.getRequestScope("beaninrequest"))

         $reqbean.string

         <br>

        #foreach($item in $reqbean.array) 
            $item <br>
        #end

</vel:velocity>
]]></source>

<p>
Again, pretty straightforward.
</p>

</section>

<section name="Building The Velocity Taglib">

<p>
To use the Velocity taglib, you need to build it, as it is not 
yet included in the main Velocity jar.  In the Jakarta tradition,
we made it very easy to build.  The code for the project is 
located in the contrib section of the distribution under 
<code>/contrib/temporary/veltag</code>.  It is under the 
temporary directory as it is hoped this package will
be accepted by the 
<a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/taglibs/">Jakarta Taglibs</a>
project.
</p>

<a name="JJAR build"><strong>The Easy, JJAR Way</strong></a>

<p>
The Veltag taglib can be built using a new, <b>experimental</b> 
jar management tool called <em>JJAR</em>
(Jakarta Jar Archive &amp; Repository) which makes finding and retrieving the
dependencies to build the taglib simple.
</p>

<p>
 <i>Please note that JJAR is 
currently a work in progress - while every effort will be made to ensure
that the JJAR-based build works, it may not always be so.  In that case, 
do it the regular way, listed below.</i>
</p>

<p>
To build with JJAR :
</p>

<ol>
<li> 
  <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/ant/">Ant</a>, the fabulous
  Jakarta build tool, must be installed.
</li>
<li>
   Get the Velocity distribution from CVS or a nightly snapshot.
</li>
<li>
   Change directory to the <code>/contrib/temporary/veltag</code>
   directory in the Velocity distribution.
</li>
<li>
   Type :
    <pre>
      $ ant getjars
    </pre>
    This will fetch JJAR and then use JJAR to fetch the dependencies du
    jour for Veltag.
</li>
<li>
   Type :
     <pre>
      $ant jar
     </pre>
    which will build the veltag-XX.jar (XX = current version).
</li>
</ol>

<p>
That's it.  Pretty easy.
</p>

<a name="nonJJAR build"><strong>The JJAR-Is-A-Work-In-Progress Way</strong></a>

<p>
In the event the JJAR-based build is broken, or you just enjoy
schlepping around finding jars, do the following to build Veltag.
</p>

<p>
To build, you need the following :
</p>

<ul>
<li> 
  <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/ant/">Ant</a>, the fabulous
  Jakarta build tool, must be installed.
</li>
<li>
  You will need a servlet API jar.  We recommend you get it from
  <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/builds/jakarta-tomcat/release/v3.2.3/bin/">here</a> 
  for servlet 2.2 and
  <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/builds/jakarta-servletapi-4/nightly/">here</a>
  for the unreleased servlet 2.3 API.  Note - if you are a JSP user, you will have 
  one included with your servlet engine.
</li>
<li> 
   A velocity.jar.  This can be found, of course,
  <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/velocity/">here</a>.
</li>
<li> 
  The build script expects to find the servlet and velocity jars in the
  <code>/contrib/temporary/veltag/lib/</code>
   directory.  Modification
  of the build script is easy if they are in another location.  Look for
  'servlet.home' and 'velocity.home' in the 
  <code>/contrib/temporary/veltag/build.xml</code> file.
</li>
<li>
  Once the above is complete, cd into 
  <code>/contrib/temporary/veltag</code> in the Velocity
  distribution and type 'ant'.  The jar should build
  for you.
</li>
</ul>
</section>

<section name="Configuration">

<p>
Using the taglib is very straightforward.  The following assumes
that you have setup a servlet container with JSP support, such as 
<a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/tomcat/">Tomcat</a>, and know
enough to write and view a simple JSP page.  Also, all directory 
references are relative to the root of the veltag project, not 
the Velocity distribution.
</p>

<p>
To test the Velocity Taglib :
</p>

<blockquote>
   You need to copy the veltag-XX.jar to the
   <code>WEB-INF/lib</code> directory of your webapp. (Where XX 
   is the current version number.
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
   Take the example taglib descriptor,
   <code> /examples/veltag.tld</code> and place in WEB-INF of your
   webapp.
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
  Finally, add 
  <pre>
    &lt;taglib&gt;
      &lt;taglib-uri&gt;http://jakarta.apache.org/taglibs/veltag-1.0&lt;/taglib-uri&gt;
      &lt;taglib-location&gt;/WEB-INF/veltag.tld&lt;/taglib-location&gt;
    &lt;/taglib&gt;
  </pre>
  to your web.xml file, within the &lt;webapp&gt; section.
</blockquote>

<p>
If you wish to use the included example JSP, you will also need to compile
<code>examples/SimpleBean.java</code> and place the resulting 
<code>SimpleBean.class</code> into the <code>WEB-INF/classes</code>
directory in your webapp.
</p>

<p>
  After that, try the example JSP found in <code>examples/</code>.  Drop it
  into the root of your webapp and view it with your browser. Enjoy!
</p>

<p>
Please direct all comments, questions, fixes and contributions to 
<a href="mailto:geirm@apache.org?SUBJECT=Veltag">Geir Magnusson Jr.</a> or the
Velocity user list.  To subscribe to the Velocity lists, read 
<a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/site/mail.html">this</a> and follow the 
instructions at the end.
</p>

<p>
  Please note that this code is not an official part of the Velocity
  distribution.
</p>

</section>

</body>
</document>

